35 קל"ה, Kuf Lamed Hey, we pick up at the bottom of
קל"ד Kuf Lamed Dalet or the middle of קל"ד עמוד ב, Kuf
Lamed Dalet Amud Bet, and the issue has been explaining the משנה
Mishna that the משנה Mishna says that a man is believed to
say that a certain person is his son. We had an earlier
משנה Mishna that a man is believed to say that somebody known
as his son is his בכור, Bechor, his firstborn. That was based
on a פסוק. Pasuk. But here we have a man who is
believed to say a certain person is his son but not that
somebody's his brother—we'll get to the brother part later, that's to say
that he gets a portion in the father's inheritance—but to say that
somebody's his son means he gets a portion in this man's inheritance.
So the גמרא Gemara says, well that's pretty obvious, he could just
gift the guy the property, so of course he's believed to say
he's his son. So the גמרא Gemara says no, the נפקא מינה
Nafka mina is for estate taxes. No, I'm just kidding. Anyway, no,
the גמרא Gemara actually says that it's true in terms of property,
it's pretty obvious, although even there there's a חידוש Chiddush
because, or not a חידוש Chiddush I should say, there's a limit
to that. Because a person is not fundamentally believed that somebody's a
son. It is only based on the principle that he could gift
it to him. So therefore, if he says 'this person's my son,'
that works for getting a portion in the property this person has
right now, but not in property this person will get later in
his life. So if there's a question, I mean, you know, if
somebody is perceived and known in the community as a child, as
a son, as a daughter, that's מוחזק, Muchzak, the guy doesn't have
to say anything. But if there's a question, and the person's only
based on the person's statement, then if he wants to make sure
that this kid gets all of the property or his right portion
of the property, he should regularly repeat this statement at regular times
so that it covers property since the last time he said it.
But that's to be believed to say that somebody's his son for
the property issue. But the גמרא Gemara says that the big חידוש
Chiddush is to say that somebody's his son in order for issues
of ייבום. Yibum. That if his wife was known that he has
brothers and it's not known that he has children—this is not only
son, could be daughter—he's believed to say that this person is his
son, his daughter, and so on, to exempt his wife from ייבום,
Yibum, and it goes against the חזקה Chazaka that his wife is
obligated in ייבום. Yibum. Why is it that it would go against
this חזקה? Chazaka? So the גמרא Gemara says because בידו לגרשה. B'yado
l'garsha. Since he has the power to divorce his wife and therefore
he could make her free from ייבום Yibum that way, he's believed
to say this. Now, this could be read as a normal מיגו,
Migo, that 'believe me that I'm saying this because why would I
bother to lie? You know, I could accomplish it through some other
way through just divorcing my wife.' Of course, from that perspective, it's
not so understandable because there might be a lot of reasons you
don't want to divorce your wife, right? So this is a much
better thing to say than to divorce your wife. So I think
a better way to understand it is the principle known sometimes in
הלכה Halacha as a idea of like בידו. B'yado. Since I can
control it,
I have the power to make my wife free from ייבום Yibum
if I wanted to by divorcing her, therefore that gives me the
trustworthiness and believability within this area of הלכה. Halacha. So since I
can make her free from ייבום Yibum if I wanted to, therefore
this is like
I'm an authority in this area, or a position of power in
this area, and therefore that somehow gives my claims believability, not just
because specifically I could do this if I wanted to, but it's
an area that I have control over, and therefore I am believed
to say that I have children, that my wife is free from
ייבום. Yibum. So that's where we left off in the גמרא. Gemara.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn from this to
other claims a husband might make about his wife because he has
the ability to divorce his wife. Okay, so let's take a
look. The גמרא Gemara says like this,
איתמר, Itmar, we'll pick up from איתמר Itmar about ten lines down
on קל"ד עמוד ב, Kuf Lamed Dalet Amud Bet, אי איתמר הכי
איתמר, Ei itmar hachi itmar, if it was said, here's how it
was said. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
מפני מה אמרו זה בני נאמן, M'pnei mah amru zeh bni ne'eman,
why did they say 'this is my son' is believed regarding ייבום
Yibum issues? הואיל ובידו לגרשה, Ho'il u'b'yado l'garsha, since he could divorce
his wife and make his wife free from ייבום Yibum that way,
he's believed in this capacity to say that she's free from ייבום
Yibum by claiming this person is his son or his daughter. Okay,
now once we've established that, אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, says
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, השתא דאמרת אמרינן הואיל, Hashta d'amarta amrinan ho'il,
now that you say we say הואיל, Ho'il, that since you could
divorce your wife you're believed in similar matters,
בעל שאמר גרשתי את אשתי נאמן, Ba'al she'amar gerashti et ishti ne'eman,
if a man just says 'I divorced my wife,' nobody's producing any
paper, any evidence, he just says 'I divorced my wife,' he's believed
הואיל ובידו לגרשה, Ho'il u'b'yado l'garsha, since he could achieve the same
end result, so therefore he's believed about this as well. And that's
a bigger נפקא מינה, Nafka mina, it's not only then if he
dies or whatever, then this woman could go ahead and could marry
somebody else, right, and the kids wouldn't be ממזרים Mamzeirim and all
these things, just based on the husband's say-so because he could achieve
that result if he wanted to.
And even if the wife is saying that 'I never got a
גט'?
Get No, presumably, it's a good question, right, it's a good question,
presumably if the wife is denying getting a גט, Get, I mean,
there's other areas where you have this, like a whole question about
believing a
מוחה. Mocheh. Midwife is a little different because midwife she's not in
a position to make it happen, but she is in a unique
position to know. But like a seller, which person did he sell
it to? Since he was in a position to decide who to
sell it to. So it's like an area of הלכה halacha of
scene of like בידו, biyado, but you're right, like, you know, to
what degree would it be depend on, you know,
counterclaims? So presumably if the woman claims otherwise it would be different.
It's a good question. But,
but right, this is he's
believed now again, it can't be a simple מיגו. migo. It's always
a lot easier to say you did something than to actually do
it. Did you clean your room? Yes! It's always easier to say
you did it than to actually do it. So anyway, but again,
it seems to be this like principle of בידו. biyado. Alright, so
anyway, so that's the claim. He's if he says he divorced his
wife, he's believed. Now, כי אתא רב יצחק ki asa Rav Yitzchak
now this though however is going to be contested. כי אתא רב
יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן. ki asa Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef
amar Rabbi Yochanan. So when רב יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar
Yosef said, he said a different claim in the name of רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Wait, was the first one in the name of
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? רב Rav
right, so that was just רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, right. Okay, so
this is in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. בעל שאמר
גרשתי אשתי אינו נאמן. Ba'al she'amar gerashti ishti eino ne'eman.
He's not believed. Okay, so then מנפח רב ששת בידיה. menapei'ach Rav
Sheshes biyadei. So רב ששת Rav Sheshes like blew with his hands
like pfft, he did like this. Pfft. That's what he did. Okay.
And he said, אזלו ליה ההואיל דרב יוסף. azlu lei haho'il d'Rav
Yosef. Goodbye, there goes רב יוסף's Rav Yosef הואיל. ho'il. There it
goes. It's a great little image. רב יוסף Rav Yosef said הואיל
בידו לגרשה, ho'il biyado legarsha, pfft
like that. So much for that. We don't say הואיל בידו לגרשה
ho'il biyado legarsha makes him believed. Now, the question is, are we
fundamentally denying the principle of הואיל בידו לגרשה? ho'il biyado legarsha? We
can't fundamentally deny that, because we have our משנה mishnah that says
that a man is believed to say who is his son, and
we're claiming at least that that includes cases of יבום. yibbum. And
the only reason he'd be believed for cases of יבום yibbum is
this principle of הואיל בידו לגרשה. ho'il biyado legarsha. So
רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafos both say it is not a fundamental
rejection of that principle, it's a rejection of the application of the
principle. What should be the difference of applying it to the case
of יבום, yibbum, or as
a claim that this is my son, versus applying it to the
claim that I divorced my wife? So based on another גמרא Gemara
they say that it's that gets back to Michael's point and gets
to questions he asked yesterday, that the case of I divorced my
wife has more counter-evidence against it. Not just what she's claiming, even
if she's agreeing. The absence of any documentation and the absence of
anybody knowing about it, like, you know, the absence of a קול,
kol, sometimes, you know, the absence of evidence is evidence, or not
total evidence, but it's certainly, you know, an indication of something. So
therefore that sort of undermines the believability of the claim that he
divorced his wife. If you had really divorced your wife, somebody would
have a גט, get, בית דין beis din would have had documentation,
people would have known about it. So therefore, even though it's בידו
לגרשה, biyado legarsha, it's
we're very skeptical of this. As opposed to the claim that this
kid is my son, which is like, you know, there are people
that can be fathered a lot of children and nobody knows who
that this person is the father. And who knows, maybe he had
this kid in מדינת הים? Medinas Hayam? It's much more I mean,
it's a little ironic, but it is easier to understand that somebody
is a son and nobody knew about it and it was all
very quiet.
Like you were saying someone else's son. What? If I say that
you're Katzriel's my kid...
Oh, please. Anyway, right, I understand. So that's an interesting question because
then it's also a claim of ממזרות. mamzerus. Okay? And I don't
think that we would have a claim that somebody it's a very
good question you asked, right? Would somebody be believed enough to פטר
patter his wife from יבום yibbum if it came through on the
heels of saying that somebody who was a child of a married
woman of a woman married to another person was his son through
having to believe a claim of ממזרות? mamzerus? I would doubt it.
I would doubt that that would we would be willing to believe
him to, you know, to affect that type of status change effectively,
you know, regarding somebody else. So I don't think we're making that
claim. But it's a good question, like, you know, again, what is
the extent of this? Anyway, that's the point of the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara is, yes we say הואיל בידו לגרשה, ho'il biyado
legarsha, it works to say somebody's a son for יבום yibbum purposes.
Now, of course, the other difference you could make is how weighty
is it what we're trying to counter? For יבום yibbum we're trying
to say that it's permissible for this woman to marry without going
through a process of חליצה, chalitzah, which is an איסור לאו. issur
lav. To say that this woman is divorced is an איסור, issur,
you know, מיתה, misa, that she's an אשת איש eisheis ish and
the kids would be ממזרים. mamzerim. There's no ממזרות mamzerus if a
woman didn't do יבום. yibbum. I mean, so so also the weight
of what we're trying, you know, to believe his statement to counter
what type of a weighty, you know, consequence is also different. But
רש"י, Rashi, רשב"ם, Rashbam, and תוספות Tosafos both don't talk about the
weight of אשת איש, eisheis ish, they just talk about the fact
that the absence of any knowledge of this, you know, the you
know,
sort of is argument against it. So therefore, he's not believed to
say he divorced his wife, but the הואיל ho'il does exist, it
exists when he makes believable claims. So when he says this is
my son. it would be believed. Michael raises good questions about maybe
there are cases where it's not believable or we don't want to
believe it in the case of this is my son, but in
general it would be believed. Michael raises good questions about maybe there
are cases where it's not believable or we don't want to believe
it in the case of this is my son, but anyway in
a standard case we will believe it. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, so this is the question, is a husband
believed to say he divorced his wife? So the גמרא Gemara is
going to continue with it. איני, Eini, is this really true? והאמר
רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abin
amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי חייא בר אבין Rabbi Chiya bar Abin says
in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan a different claim in
the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. בעל שאמר גירשתי את אשתי
נאמן, Baal she-amar gerashti es ishti ne-eman, the exact opposite in the
name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that a husband is believed to
say he divorced his wife. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן למפרע כאן להבא. kan l'mafrea kan
l'haba. So now we are saying actually we're backtracking from what we
said before. The husband really is believed to say he divorced his
wife, and that's this claim of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So what
did the earlier claim mean that the husband isn't believed to say
he divorced his wife? Retroactively. Okay here a man gets up, ראובן
Reuven gets up and his wife is found to have committed adultery
and he says oh I divorced her a year ago. Okay so
he's not believed. Why is he not believed? Because it's not בידו
לגרשה b'yado l'garsha a year ago. A year ago it was בידו
לגרשה, b'yado l'garsha, but right now unless you have some in with
the principle of relativity, right now you don't have the ability to
divorce your wife a year ago. So therefore you're not believed to
say you divorced her a year ago, you're only believed to say
you divorced her as of today. So according to this we're going
back to what we said before. A husband fundamentally is believed to
say he divorced his wife. The only time he's not believed is
if he makes the claim that it happened earlier. Okay then since
he can't make it happen earlier right where he's standing right now
he has no believability about the past. He's only believed from this
point going forward. So now the גמרא Gemara asks an obvious question.
איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, we raise the question.
אמר למפרע מהו להימוני להבא.
Amar l'mafrea mahu
l'heimunei l'haba. Okay guy gets up and he says and there's no
case of adultery or whatever and he says I divorced my wife
last week. All right so for anything that occurred in the last
week that statement is meaningless. Fine but we don't really care about
last week, we care about starting today. Can she go ahead and
marry another man? Will it be a ממזרות? mamzerus? If the guy
dies is the woman obligated in יבום? yibum? Is he at least
believed from today going forward? Okay so that is a good question.
Do we have to take his whole statement as one unit? And
since we can't believe the part that's effective a week ago we
can't believe it at all? We have to just say well this
statement isn't believed, goodbye. Or do we say no we don't believe
it as it applies to the past, we'll believe it as it
applies to the present and the future. So that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. מי פלגינן דיבורא או לא פלגינן. Mi palginan dibura o lo
palginan. Do we split his words or not? Do we sort of
believe them at least if not from the past at least going
forward? Now sometimes split his words could mean in a very literal
sense. He said I divorced my wife last week. So let's just
cut off your sentence at the word my wife, period, or cut
out the words last week.
Okay that would be one way of sort of literally. But the
other way is it doesn't even matter how he phrased it. Even
if he phrased it in a way that we couldn't cut out
the words, do we basically just like are we able to apply
it for certain things and not apply it for other things? It
doesn't have to literally mean we can cut his sentence different ways.
Okay so will we able to be apply it from here going
forward even if we can't apply it to the past? That's the
question. מי פלגינן דיבורא או לא פלגינן דיבורא. Mi palginan dibura o
lo palginan dibura. רב מרי ורב זביד, Rav Mari ve-Rav Zvid, so
the גמרא Gemara says רב מרי ורב זביד, Rav Mari ve-Rav Zvid,
חד אמר פלגינן, chad amar palginan, so there's a debate between רב
מרי Rav Mari and רב זביד Rav Zvid in this case, a
husband said I divorced my wife last week. One says we split
the words and חד אמר לא פלגינן, chad amar lo palginan, we
don't split the words.
Now מכדי מאי דראבא, michdi mai de-Rava, now why should we not?
We have a classic case where we do split the words. How
is it different than what רבא Rava said? דאמר רבא, de-amar Rava,
איש פלוני בא על אשתי, ish ploni ba al ishti, a man
says ראובן Reuven had sex with my wife. הוא ואחר, hu ve-acher,
so this man and somebody else and שמעון Shimon are
עדים, edim, okay מצטרפים להרגו mitztarfim l'hargo to kill ראובן, Reuven, to
basically their testimony is accepted in court and ראובן Reuven is now
convicted as an adulterer. ראובן Reuven is executed, his wife is not
because the testimony is not accepted vis-a-vis his wife because he's a
קרוב karov to his wife. But if he just said ראובן Reuven
committed adultery with a woman whose identity I don't know but I
can tell you she's an אשת איש, aishesh ish, that would be
believed. So we can ignore the identity of the woman, make her
like an anonymous woman, and therefore say he's still claiming that ראובן
Reuven committed adultery, you have two witnesses that ראובן Reuven committed adultery.
What? His wife is probably אסורה asura to him because of whatever
שויא אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא, shavya anafshei chaticha d'issura, but we're not going
to go there. But yes okay so we can take the effect
of his testimony and apply it to one person and not to
another person. So here too let's take the effect of this guy's
claim and apply it to the present and the future but not
to the past. So if everybody agrees to רבא Rava why would
there be a debate here? The גמרא Gemara says להרגו ולא להרגה,
l'hargo v'lo l'hargah, we kill him, ראובן, Reuven, but we don't kill
the wife. So the גמרא Gemara says בתרי גופי פלגינן בחד גופא
לא פלגינן. bitrei gufai palginan b'chad gufa lo palginan. No, because there
we believe the entirety of the testimony vis-a-vis ראובן. Reuven. So in
a court case, you know, this happens sometimes, right? Because you know,
you have like what happens? Like you have multiple defendants and they're
all about the same crime. Like this group of people all broke
into a house and each one has a separate court case and
you might have the same witnesses testify in the different court cases.
And in one case, actually the guy's convicted and the other case
the guy gets off, right? The other guy gets off. So regarding
ראובן Reuven as the defendant, this testimony is totally acceptable. This person
isn't a קרוב karov in the case against ראובן. Reuven. The state
against ראובן, Reuven, the person isn't a קרוב, karov, so it's totally
acceptable. In the case against his wife, he's completely not accepted as
a witness. So we can basically split the court cases and we
accept his testimony one hundred percent. Whereas in this case,
we're taking the testimony, it all applies to one woman, his wife,
and we only want to accept it for you know from now
going forward and not from the past. Maybe we can't divide it
that way.
What were we מחלק? mechaleik? We were מחלק mechaleik the testimony in
half or the application?
Well,
in both cases it's the application, but the application to one person
as opposed to another. The entire testimony is accepted as applied to
this person, completely rejected or that we are splitting the effect of
the testimony even vis-a-vis one person. Right. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, בתרי גופי פלגינן בחד גופא לא פלגינן, bitrei gufai
palginan b'chad gufa lo palginan, fine. So now,
I do want to say though that, you know, I don't know,
to me, if you had asked me intuitively, we should more believe
him in the case of the גירושין geirushin than in the case
of the adultery, besides that he might have a personal like, you
know, a strong bias to be influencing him in the case of
adultery. But even putting that aside, it's that in the case of
the testimony,
he is believed because he has a certain...
it's not like there's something that taints the claim of the past,
it's just there's no reason to believe the claim of the past.
The reason we believe what he says is בידו לגרשה b'yado l'garsha
and that's true from the present going forward. So therefore, there's a
reason to believe from the present going forward. What he said about
the past, maybe it's true, maybe it's not, but there's nothing particular
that makes it believable. So as opposed to the idea that a
claim when you're actually a relative and you know you're connected to
the events, he's a קרוב karov to his wife in the case
of the testimony of adultery, that should be like you know, that
should sort of stigmatize the entire thing. That should say, 'Throw the
whole thing out! The guy has a vested interest!' right? So to
me, my inclination would be to split it the other way. The
גמרא Gemara is sort of operating in a very sort of formalistic
way. So given the conclusion, well given that it's not clear if
we believe him
from now going forward, the רשב"ם Rashbam says even therefore according to
the side that a person who says he divorced his wife is
believed,
you know, given the question here that it would only clearly be
the case if he said, 'I divorced her today,' or he said
'I divorced her without giving a timeframe.' But as soon as he
said 'I divorced her yesterday,' even if he said 'I divorced her...'
I mean the question is how narrowly do you split it? 'I
divorced her a minute ago?' That's not good? He has to say
'I divorced her this second?' Anyway, but any claim that he did
it in the past would mean that we can't accept the claim
altogether. Yeah, Rabbi Dove, you had a question?
I was thinking about the three-month thing, but like 'I divorced her
last week' and then she got remarried two days later. Right. So
that would be an אשת איש eishet ish situation. Right.
Okay. Yeah and then
he would not be... well no, he clearly is not believed about
anything that happened prior to his statement,
but the question is if he says 'I divorced her last week'
and then tomorrow she goes and she gets married to another man,
according to one version here the kids are ממזרים mamzerim and she's
committed adultery. So it's a pretty big נפקא מינא. nafka mina. Yeah.
I don't understand this case about the adulterer in terms of if
he's going to be executed.
How can he be executed if he's ostensibly married to her?
He did sleep with a married woman. We just don't know the
identity of the married woman. Or if you want to say it
another way, in the case against ראובן Reuven we believe he slept
with שרה. Sarah. Okay? As ראובן Reuven as the defendant.
Let's say שרה Sarah was dead, okay? Then he could testify that
ראובן Reuven slept with his wife שרה Sarah because she's dead now,
right? So it's the same difference. Even though he can't testify against
שרה, Sarah, this isn't the case against שרה. Sarah. So within the
case against ראובן, Reuven, he's believed to testify that he slept with
שרה. Sarah. He is testifying that he slept with a married woman,
but we're just not dealing with the case against the married woman,
so he's not being thrown out as a פסול pasul witness.
But if she's not going to be executed, right? Then he didn't
commit adultery?
No, that's not true. First of all, he did commit adultery, we
just can't prove it about her. We can prove it about him.
Okay, I
mean. But also let's say he slept with a minor, that's a
classic case, okay, a minor who was married, right, because she was
married by her father, you wouldn't prosecute the girl, you prosecute the
guy. Or let's say he raped a married woman, you would execute
the guy, you wouldn't execute the woman, right? So there's a lot
of cases in which you can execute one person and or you
know and not the other, because we don't have enough evidence because
the person wasn't in a state of being liable.
Right, exactly. Alright, so let's go on. ההוא דהוי קשכיב, Hahu de-hava
kashchiv, okay, top of קל"ה עמוד א'. Kuf Lamed Hey Amud Aleph.
ההוא דהוי קשכיב. Hahu de-hava kashchiv.
Wait they said at the end of the day, since we're not
resolving
this, since
we're not resolving it we have to be... right, although we probably
wouldn't execute a woman on the basis of it, I mean the
kid would wind up being a ספק ממזר safek mamzer I guess,
you know, it would be a ספק. safek. ההוא דהוי, Hahu de-hava,
there was a person, what, yeah that's it, ההוא, Hahu, well we
still have a little more to go, ההוא דהוי קשכיב, Hahu de-hava
kashchiv, a guy was, yeah.
I know we're not asking for the שטר shtar for a גט,
get, but the זמן? zman? I know that... yes so תוספות Tosafot
asks that,
like if he was believed... no, the זמן zman is not דאורייתא,
de-Oraita, but the זמן zman in a גט get was made in
order that a person could not claim he divorced his wife prior
to when he did, so תוספות Tosafot says, so then it's pretty
obvious that he's not believed retroactively, right, because obviously then there wouldn't
be, you wouldn't need to have the date in a גט, get,
a person could always just claim. So that's how תוספות Tosafot makes
that point. ההוא דהוי קשכיב. Hahu de-hava kashchiv. A person was dying.
אמרו ליה, Amru lei, איתתא למאן? itteta le-man? What's the story with
your wife, can she... like we know that there are brothers, is
she, does she have to do ייבום yibbum or can she marry
whoever she wants?
Did you divorce her or not?
Yeah did you divorce her, do you have kids? Not exactly clear
what we're asking but one or the other. אמרו להו, Amru le-hu,
he said to those people, חזיא לכהנא רבא, chazya le-kahana rabba, my
wife could even marry the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Now of course
she can't marry the כהן גדול kohen gadol because she'll be
an אלמנה, almanah, okay, means that she can marry whoever she wants,
okay, there's no ייבום yibbum problem. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so Rava
said, מאי ניחוש לה, mai nichush lah, what do we have to
worry about? So the person is believed, he presumably believed that a
person was believed to say גירשתי את אשתי gerashti et ishti and
again, the claim here is, now the question is, he doesn't make
a specific claim. How do we interpret what his claim is? He's
saying she's fit to marry. Is he claiming he divorced her? Or
is he claiming that he has sons? So basically based on the
גמרא Gemara it sounds like he's going to be claiming, we're going
to read it, choose to read it that he's claiming that he
divorced her, because since the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains the case
is, we have a חזקה chazakah that he doesn't have sons, we'd
rather not read this silence, you know, this unclear statement. If he
explicitly says 'I have sons,' he's believed, but we're not going to
choose to read this vague statement to say that 'I have sons'
if we have a חזקה chazakah that he doesn't have sons. What
we will read it to say is that he divorced his wife,
because that is something that he could always do, okay, rather than
reading against a perception and an assumption that we have.
He's not on his ערש דוי? eres davai?
He is on his ערש דוי. eres davai.
So then I would assume that it was about having sons, because
why do you have to read it that he divorced her? He's
going to die.
What, well people would often give a... so people would... oh, you
mean because then she's going to lose out in terms of the
estate? Well, yeah that's true, I mean she would suffer as a
result of that claim. But again, so but it's because we would
rather read his claim to not go against our assumption of what
the facts are. And our assumption of the facts are is that
he has no sons, whereas we don't know even though we know
she's been married, it could always change in a day. So anyway,
that's... but I hear your point, that if we read it that
he's divorced, will she be believed to cut her out of the,
you know, sort of being supported by the estate? That's a good
question. I hear the point. Okay, let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי ניחוש לה? mai nichush lah? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, בשעה
שאמר גירשתי את אשתי נאמן. besha'ah she-amar gerashti et ishti ne'eman. He's
believed, presumably because like we said, we've now switched it to say
he is believed at least going forward, and we're going to read
that into what he said. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abbaye, והא
כי אתא רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן, ve-ha ki ata
Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan, בשעה שאמר גירשתי את אשתי
אינו נאמן. besha'ah she-amar gerashti et ishti eino ne'eman. But we have
a different tradition in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that
he's not believed. So why are you picking the tradition that he
is believed? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him,
ולאו מי לא שנינהו, ve-lav mi lo shaninhu, כאן למפרע וכאן להבא?
kan le-mafre'a ve-chan le-haba? But we resolve those two. We said he's
believed going forward, he's not believed retroactively. And here his claim was
not that he did it last week, you know, he was not
specific about the time. And since he was not specific about the
time, we're going to say that it's a believable statement, you know,
as long as he's not specifically saying he did it in the
past.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him,
אשינויא ניקום ונסמוך? a-shinuyya nekum ve-nismoch? What, we're just going to rely
on some answer? Which is great, you know, what do you mean
we're going to rely on some answer, that's always what the גמרא
Gemara does, it asks a question, it gives an answer. But the
point is, okay, one way to resolve it was to say everybody
agrees בשעה besha'ah he is believed as long as he's not making
a... But it's quite possible that there's a debate of אמוראים Amoraim
what רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position is. That there's not, we shouldn't
be resolving it. Maybe it's a real debate. And according to some,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said a husband is never believed to say
he divorced his wife. And according to that, this woman would not
be believed to go ahead and to marry without חליצה. chalitza. Okay?
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him, אמא
סו, ama so, אמר ליה רבא לרב נתן בר אמי, amar lei
Rava l'Rav Natan bar Ami, so that led רבא Rava to retract
or to go back and say, חושלא. chushla. All right, we have
to be concerned,
maybe we don't believe his claim, maybe she's actually not divorced and
she needs יבום. yibbum. So חושלא chushla parallels the opening of the
statement of רבא, Rava, מאי נחוש לה? mai neichosh lah? What do
we have to be concerned about? And then he says, oh, טאקע,
taka, we do have to be concerned. Okay, so חושלא. chushla. All
right, so here, right, the גמרא Gemara keeps on seesawing back and
forth whether הבעל שאמר גירשתי את אשתי נאמן. ha'baal she'amar gerashti et
ishti ne'eman. Rather than saying he is believed except retroactively, here we're
saying that maybe it's a debate if he's believed and maybe we
have to be concerned according to the position that he's not. Now
again, all the ראשונים Rishonim say he certainly is would be believed
to say I have sons to פטור patter his wife from יבום.
yibbum. That's our משנה. Mishna. A husband that says יש לי בנים
yesh li banim is נאמן. ne'eman. Again, the only claim is he's
not believed to say he divorced his wife because the absence of
evidence is seen as a סימן siman to indicate that he probably
didn't divorce his wife. Okay, the fact that nobody knows about it,
that there's no שטר, shtar, there's no קול. kol. So therefore, it's
specifically the claim that he divorced his wife that is contradicted, that
is not believed. A claim that he had children would be believed.
Now again, what is ironic is, and this goes back to Dov's
question, is that since he was vague and he said, nah, she
can marry whoever she wants, okay, so why should we interpret that
to say I
divorced my wife? Oh, now we can't believe him because he's not
believed to say he divorced his wife. Why read it in the
version, in the interpretation that won't be believed? Why not read it
to say she can marry whoever she wants because I have kids?
And therefore that will be believed, right? So that really even heightens
the question. Because it's one thing if it's like either way it'll
be believed and maybe there's an advantage or a disadvantage, but at
least we'll read it in the way that doesn't contradict our חזקה.
chazaka. But here to say I divorced my wife, we won't believe
him. If he said I had sons, we would. Let's read it
that way. And it seems so much that because our חזקה chazaka
is that he doesn't have children, unless he makes a direct claim
against that חזקה, chazaka, okay, we are not going to read it
to say that he has children and the end result will be
his wife needs חליצה. chalitza. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר ליה רבא לרב נתן, amar lei Rava l'Rav Natan,
we just did that. ההוא דהוה מוחזק לן דלית ליה אחי. hahu
d'hava muchzak lan d'leit lei achi. One more story about this, a
parallel story. A certain person we had a חזקה chazaka that he
had no brothers. That was our perception of him, that he had
no brothers.
Okay, ואמר בשעת מיתה דלית ליה אחי. v'amar b'sha'at mita d'leit lei
achi. And he reinforced this as he was dying, he said, I
have no brothers. Okay, so his wife is doubly exempt from יבום.
yibbum. One because that was just our assumption, and number two is
he even made that claim explicitly as he was dying. Okay, so,
and so, and that claim similarly would be believed, you know, because
he could, again, בידו לגרשה, b'yado l'garsha,
he could make her פטור pattur from יבום yibbum by being מגרש
megaresh her. He would be believed to say he doesn't have brothers,
as long as it's not against the evidence or maybe against the
חזקה. chazaka.
Okay, what does it mean to say he was מוחזק muchzak that
he didn't have brothers?
That was our perception of him.
In other words, he lived in the מקום makom
for generations and he never spoke about a brother. Every time there
was a family שמחה, simcha, nobody on his side of the family
was invited. Okay, so that was our perception. Okay, and, okay, and
the, by the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam points out and this wasn't
discussed earlier, that even if he was מוחזק muchzak to have brothers,
מוחזק muchzak as opposed to direct knowledge, even if there was a
perception that he had brothers, he would be believed to say he
doesn't have brothers. Again, בידו לגרשה. b'yado l'garsha. The same way he's
believed to say he has sons even if there's a perception that
he doesn't have sons to get his wife off of יבום, yibbum,
he'd be believed to say he doesn't have brothers even if there's
a perception that he does. Perception as opposed to absolute knowledge. So
now we have two reasons to think his wife is פטור יבום.
pattur yibbum. Number one, there was never a, he, the perception was
he doesn't have brothers. Number two, he claims he doesn't have brothers,
which has believability to it because בידו לגרשה. b'yado l'garsha. Okay, so,
so the גמרא Gemara says, and then he died. And the question
was the status of his wife. Okay, אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav
Yosef, מאי לחוש לה? mai leichosh lah? What do we have to
be concerned about? You know, that that's a set up. חדא דמוחזק
לן דלית ליה אחי. chada d'muchzak lan d'leit lei achi. Number one,
we have a חזקה chazaka he has no brothers. ועוד, v'od, number
two,
הא אמר בשעת מיתה. ha amar b'sha'at mita. Two good reasons to
say his wife is exempt. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, okay,
I get you. But הא אמרי דאיכא עדים במדינת הים דידעי ליה
אחי. ha amri deika eidim bimdinas hayam deyaddi lei achi. But there's
a rumor out there that there are witnesses in China that actually
have concrete knowledge that he has a brother. Okay, so it's not
saying we know that, you know, as a fact for fact that
there are witnesses that testified then we know that he's got a
brother, end of story. Okay, but there's a rumor that there are
witnesses that know that there's a rumor that there's some evidence in
some file somewhere that will actually some birth certificate that actually will
prove that he has a brother. Can we let his wife remarry
without חליצה chalitzah before or do we have to wait until we
can get to those witnesses in China or until we can investigate
and get ahold of that file and find out if such a
birth certificate actually
exists?
Okay. Reasonable doubt.
There's, well, or
לעז הספק. la'as hasafeik. Right. There's a לעז, la'as, but the question
is right now the חזקה chazakah and his claim is that he
doesn't have. Now, even if and his belief that he doesn't have
brothers would be believed even against a חזקה chazakah that he has
brothers. But the point is, we're saying it's not that there's a
חזקה, chazakah, there might be actual evidence, real hard evidence. How much
do we have to be concerned about that? Or do we say
we go by what we know right now? And based on what
we know right now, he doesn't have, he doesn't have brothers and
she can remarry. So the answer is, okay. השתא, Hashta,
so the גמרא Gemara says, הא אמרי דאיכא עדים במדינת הים דידעי
ליה אחי, ha amri deika eidim bimdinas hayam deyaddi lei achi, השתא
מהכא לית נינהו קמן. hashta meihacha leis ninhu kamman. Oh, but so
what? Right now the witnesses aren't there! We don't have to care
about them. Okay, some rumor that there are witnesses is not going
to hold up. You can understand it's highly unfair, right? You know,
it's like אין לדיין אלא מה שעיניו רואות. ein ladayan ela mah
she'einav ro'os. Anytime there's some rumor, all of a sudden it puts
the, you know, it stops life from moving forward? Right now the
witnesses aren't here. לאו היינו דרבי חנינא? Lav hainu di-Rabbi Chanina? This
is like the story of רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. דאמר רבי חנינא,
De-amar Rabbi Chanina, עדים בצד אצתן ותיאסר? eidim be-tzad Etztan vete'aser?
If witnesses are somewhere in אצתן, Etztan, which is somewhere like far
away in the north, should this woman be forbidden? The case was
שמואל's Shmuel daughter was taken as a captive, and she came back
and she said, "Yes, I was taken as a captive, וטהורה אני.
u-tehorah ani. I have not been raped, I did not have intercourse
with my captors and so on," and therefore she was permitted to
go ahead and to marry a כהן. kohen. Because since she was,
it was פה שאסר פה שהתיר. peh she-asar peh she-hitir. She was
the only person testifying that she was captive, and she was saying
that she was טהורה אני. tehorah ani. Okay, but then the גמרא
Gemara says, but one minute, there's a rumor that there are עדים
eidim that she actually was taken as captive and that, you know,
and that she was raped or whatever. So maybe we should wait
to hear from those witnesses in China? To which, you know, רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina said back, עדים eidim are somewhere in, you know,
Yennemsville and we're going to say that she has to be forbidden?
The witnesses aren't here, we're not going to worry about some rumor
of some witnesses. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so isn't that
an obvious application of this principle? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said no, not necessarily.
אי הקלנו בשבויה, In hikalnu bishvuyah, just because we're lenient by the
case of a woman taken captive, which is not definitely even if
she was taken captive, it's only a ספק safek if she had
intercourse with this non-Jew, if she was raped or whatever, and therefore
it's a really it's only rabbinically would she be forbidden to a
כהן. kohen. So that's a rabbinic matter, that's one thing. ניקול באשת
איש? Neikul be-eishes ish? Should we be lenient by a case of
a אשת איש? eishes ish? Now, I do want to say this
is not a classic אשת איש. eishes ish. Yes, this woman was
married, but now she's an אלמנה. almanah. Now it really is just
a case of a ייבום, yibum, it's not a case of adultery,
okay, it's a ייבום yibum question. Okay, but nevertheless, it's still weightier
than a שבויה shvuyah question. So okay, maybe it's something that is
more weighty, maybe we need to try to find out and get
those witnesses. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה רבא לרב נתן
בר אמי חוש לה. amar lei Rava le-Rav Nassan bar Ami chush
lah. Oh, so it unfortunately it ended in the same unfortunate way
as the other one landed. Okay, we have to, we do have
to be concerned. So actually if there is a concern of concrete
hard evidence about something and it's a weighty issue, we can't just
go forward. We actually have to investigate. Now the question still is,
to what degree? First of all, let's say you know it's going
to take ten years, okay. Let's say or let's say we tried
to investigate, we made some inquiries, we called up the police in
China, we sent some letters and nobody answered, blah, blah, blah, we
did our due diligence, we tried and we're not getting any and
it's not producing anything, like are you then allowed to go forward?
Right? So like some of those really core questions are not being
answered. Yes,
Charlie?
אין לדבר סוף, Ein la-davar sof, there's no end to the matter
here. I mean, someone could come up with a rumor.
Right, so that's another question also, what does it mean that there's
a rumor? If somebody סתם stam shows up to בית דין beis
din and says, "I heard," is that good enough or does it
have to be some widespread perception? of this fact? Right, so אמרי,
amri, people are saying. How many people have to say? One person,
two people, twenty people? Right, all of the parameters here are very
unclear. All right, now we move on. זה וכי אינו נאמן. Ze
vechi eino ne'eman. Second part of the mishnah, which is, this guy
claims here, Reuven claims, Reuven and Shimon were the only known brothers.
Reuven says, "Oh yeah, Levi is a brother of ours." And Shimon
says, "Not as far as I know." So the point is, so
Shimon does not so they each got one and a half fields
from their father. Since Shimon says, "I have no knowledge that Levi
is a brother, I'm not giving him from my inheritance," so Reuven's
claim is not believed against Shimon. That if he says Levi is
a brother, he's not believed. But he is believed against himself. According
to your claim, Reuven, Levi should be getting
a half field from you. He should be getting another from Shimon.
We can't make that happen, but at least you have to give
him, you know, that piece that you claim he deserves from the
inheritance you received. That's the case of the mishnah. אינו נאמן ונוטל
עמו בחלקו. Eino ne'eman venotel imo bechelko. So says the Gemara as
follows. So Gemara says, ואידך מאי קא אמרי? Ve'idach mai ka amri?
So what's Shimon saying in this equation? אי דקא מודה לו, Ei
deka modeh lo, if Shimon is conceding that Levi's a brother obviously
he's not, but we're just sort of putting that up as a
straw man so אמאי יטול עמו בחלקו? Amai yitol imo bechelko? Then
why does Levi only get a portion with
Reuven? Shimon is conceding that he's a brother. ותו לא? Vesu lo?
And nothing more? אלא דקא אמרי לאו אחונהו. Ela deka amri lav
achunhu.
So the other brothers are saying Levi isn't a brother. So אימא
סיפא. Eima seifa. So let's look at the end. נפלו לו נכסים
ממקום אחר. Naflu lo nechasim mimakom acher. Let's say Levi goes, he
makes his fortune in the world, he makes millions of dollars and
then he dies. So then who inherits from him, and he has
no kids? It says Reuven and Shimon split his inheritance. So why
is Shimon entitled to split his inheritance if Shimon all along has
been claiming that he's not a brother? So
יירשו אחיו עמו. Yirshu echav imo. הא אמרי לאו אחונהו! Ha amri
lav achunhu!
But they're saying, "You're not our brother." So they're basically, you know,
denying any future claim to Levi's property. So, לא צריכא דקא אמרי
אינו יודעים. Lo tzricha deka amri einu yodim. Ah, they take the
smart position: "I can't
recall." Okay? So Shimon says, "I don't know if he's our brother."
So because I don't know, I'm not going to give him part
of my inheritance מספק. mi'safek. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav
haraya. But if he dies, okay, then now why don't you say,
"Okay, but how do you claim part of his property from a
doubt?" Well, Reuven is saying Levi is a brother. So Reuven is
already saying that I'm entitled to inherit half of Levi, right? Based
on Reuven's claim that Levi's a brother, then now that Levi has
made his fortune and he's died, according to Reuven's claim, he's saying
he's our brother and based on Reuven, I'm entitled to get part
of his estate. Okay? So that's true as long as I'm not
denying Reuven's claim. As long as all I'm saying is איני יודע,
eini yodeia, then I should be entitled to get part of that
estate as well. So the smart move is to say איני יודע.
eini yodeia. I don't have to give anything, but then if Levi
dies, I'm entitled to get part of Levi's estate. Okay? Because that
at least is part of what Reuven is claiming. The funny question
here is, of course, okay, which is, Levi must have some other
relatives. Right? Levi's got, I don't know, you know, now again, I
guess if the question is who his father was, you don't know
who his other relatives are. But like, anyway, the question is like,
what would be if there was a fight between now between Reuven
and the other person who was claiming that he was, you know,
Levi's relative and so on. All right, anyway. So דקא אמרי איני
יודע. deka amri eini yodeia. We don't know. So therefore we don't
have to give him from our property, but if he dies, then
since Reuven is claiming he is a brother, we're going to take
from his estate. אמר רבא זאת אומרת מנה לי בידך והלה אומר
איני יודע פטור. Amar Rava zos omeret mane li beyadecha vehala omer
eini yodeia patur.
So basically this is a case where Reuven is saying to Shimon,
"Hey, you owe Levi a half of a field." And Shimon is
saying, "I don't know. As far as I know, he's not a
brother, but I have no knowledge." So isn't that a classic case
of a ברי ושמא? bari veshema? I say I say to Charlie,
"Charlie, you owe me a hundred dollars. You borrowed a hundred dollars
from me last week." And Charlie says, "I don't remember. Maybe? Maybe
not? I don't know." So do we say that if I'm a
ברי bari and he is a שמא, shema, I am saying you
definitely and he says I don't know, but on the other hand
the money is in his pocket, does that win out against חזקה
chazaka or not? Does Charlie have to pay me or not? Okay,
the basic הלכה halacha is he doesn't have to pay me. You
know, חזקה chazaka beats out against a ברי. bari. But the question
is does this prove it? Isn't this the same thing? Reuven is
saying to Shimon, "Hey, you owe Levi a half field." And Shimon
is saying, "I don't know. I don't know if he's a brother."
And we say he doesn't have to give. So it shows you
ברי ושמא לאו ברי עדיף. bari veshema lav bari adif. So זאת
אומרת zos omeret this teaches you מנה לי בידך והלה אומר איני
יודע פטור, mane li beyadecha vehala omer eini yodeia patur, you don't
have to give. אביי אמר Abaye amar אביי Abaye says no. לעולם
אימא לך חייב. Le'olam eima lach chayav. I could tell you normally
if you say to somebody you owe me a hundred dollars and
they say I don't know, the person would have to pay you.
Okay, ושני הכא, ve-shani hacha, here it's different דכמנה לאחר בידך דמי,
de-kamaneh le-acher beyadcha d'amei, because ראובן Reuven is not saying to שמעון,
Shimon, you owe me a hundred dollars, maybe in that case if
שמעון Shimon said I don't know he'd have to give it. ראובן
Reuven is saying to שמעון, Shimon, you owe לוי Levi a hundred
dollars, you owe לוי Levi a half a field. So when does
a ברי bari claim—maybe a ברי bari claim wins out against חזקה
chazakah if I am making my own
claim, okay, but if I am saying something on behalf of לוי
Levi and לוי's Levi saying, look, I have no idea who my
father is, how am I supposed to know? You know, ראובן Reuven
claims that he knows that his father slept with my mother and
he's claiming he knows who my father is, but the גמרא's Gemara
framing it that לוי Levi himself doesn't know for sure who his
father is. לוי Levi was brought up by a single mother. He
has no idea who his father is. Comes along ראובן Reuven and
says I know who your father was, it was my father. Okay,
so ראובן Reuven is the only ברי bari here, everybody else is
a שמא. shema. Okay, so ראובן's Reuven ברי bari won't be enough
to take property away from שמעון Shimon to give it to לוי.
Levi. You need to be making your own claim in court to
win out against the other guy, okay, in the case of a
ברי bari and a שמא. shema. Alright, so that's why, no matter
what you hold in general about ברי ושמא, bari ve-shema, שמעון Shimon
does not have to give this half of a field to לוי
Levi because לוי Levi himself isn't even coming with a ברי bari
claim, the only person here with a ברי bari claim is ראובן.
Reuven.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Everybody good? Yep. Okay,
מיתי יחזרו נכסים למקומן. meisi yachzeru nechasim limkoman.
Now, if לוי Levi died and he didn't make money or whatever,
he just סתם stam earned some... well, if he makes money we
say שמעון Shimon and ראובן Reuven split it. Here's the money he
made, his own money he made, okay, so this money he made
in his own life, that gets equally split by שמעון Shimon and
ראובן Reuven because שמעון Shimon is saying איני יודע eini yode'a and
according to ראובן Reuven they're brothers and they inherit equally. But the
field that ראובן Reuven gave לוי, Levi, the half field that ראובן
Reuven gave לוי, Levi, that goes all the way back to ראובן,
Reuven, right? Because basically he basically saying hey שמעון, Shimon, he should
have had a half field from you, so the half field you
never gave him you're keeping now that he's dead and you get
his inheritance, and the half field I gave him I'm getting back,
okay? So that half field goes back to ראובן Reuven and the
new money gets split between the brothers. That clear? Yeah, why? Because
really it's true, שמעון Shimon and ראובן Reuven equally inherit him. But
you've always been holding onto that half field which you should have
given him according to ראובן Reuven a long time ago. So that
half field you've been holding onto you just keep, I'll take the
half field I gave him back, and then the new money we
split. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: בעי
רבא, ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asked, שבח ששבחו נכסים מאליהם מהו? shevach
she-shivchu nechasim me'alehem mahu? If this half field now increased in value,
is that like new money that they split it, or does that
half field just go straight back to ראובן? Reuven? Is that clear?
Okay. How do we treat that? Because maybe the real estate value
shot up here and they stayed stable here. So according to שמעון
Shimon like had we both given him the field, if I had
even given him what I should have and he had taken it
and now he died, I would be getting like half of the
increase of value here. So maybe it's—you can't just say you take
back your half, I'm taking back my half, okay? Maybe an increase
in value here has to be shared by the two of us.
So what's the story? בשבח המגיע לכתפים לא תיבעי לך. beshevach hamagi'a
liktefayim lo tiba'ei lach.
The increase that comes by the shoulders, I'm not asking. Now that's
a phrase that there's always a debate what that means. Some say
it means that you bought the field empty and now it had
like fully standing wheat, that's מגיע לכתפים, magi'a liktefayim, the wheat is
like at shoulder height. Right, so something that is clearly seen as
like it wasn't there before and it's there now, so that actually
would be equally split. Okay, that is like new property. Another way
of reading מגיע לכתפים magi'a liktefayim means it requires putting your shoulder
into it, meaning comes through effort as opposed to just happened by
itself. So anything that came through לוי Levi exerting effort and making
an investment in the field and plowing it and building on it,
all of that is new property and actually שמעון Shimon gets to
take half of that. Okay, that's not my question.
כי תיבעי לך, ki tiba'ei lach, what's my question? בשבח שאינו מגיע
לכתפים. beshevach she'eino magi'a liktefayim.
Some type of a not radically new change, okay, something that happened
naturally that the thing didn't change much. The example I gave was
that the real estate prices shot up, that would be one example,
nobody did anything to the field, okay, כגון דקלא ואלים, kegon dikla
ve-alim, like it was a palm tree that just got a little
thicker. Thicker, it's not considered a new tree, nobody invested any effort,
or ארעא דאסקיה שירטון, ara de'askia sirton, like a land that became
flooded and now the soil is richer, but nobody did anything to
it. Okay, מאי, mai, so would they split that equally, that increased
value, or does that all go back to ראובן? Reuven? So גמרא
Gemara says תיקו, teiku, leave it with we don't know. All right,
moving on. Yes.
Yeah, it went down, then that would be a good point. If
the price went down, then ראובן Reuven could say to שמעון, Shimon,
if you're going to take from this, you have to give me
half of the increase of value of that probably.
Yeah, exactly. All right, so now we move on to the next
משנה mishnah and with this next משנה mishnah we are finally really
transitioning. All along we've been referencing in passing this institution of מתנת
שכיב מרע, matnat shchiv meira, of the deathbed bequest. Now we are
finally going to deal with it at least a little bit more
directly. But even now that we're going to deal with it, we're
going to deal with a variation of it. And the variation is
something that the lawyers in the room should be familiar with, or
we all should be familiar with, which is a דיאתיקי. diatiki. דיאתיקי
Diatiki is probably some Greek word, Charlie will tell us what it
means originally.
Anyway, it is a Greek word meaning will.
Ah, meaning will! Well that's exactly what I was going to describe
it as. It's normally described as a writ, but really what it
is is a דיאתיקי diatiki is a will. It is a written
will, my last will and testament, and I hereby am granting blah
blah blah blah blah and you write it out. So, we here
conceptually in our mind, the will would be the primary instrument, right?
From the גמרא's Gemara perspective, the primary instrument is the מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnat shchiv meira, is the verbal bequest on the deathbed. But
then a variation of the verbal bequest on the deathbed is when
you actually write it out, which would be the smart thing to
do. Let's have some written evidence. Now, this does not work by
normal laws of קנין kinyan because I am not writing out I
am granting my field to Gloria here and Gloria now I give
the שטר shtar and it's a קנין kinyan on the שטר. shtar.
You know, it's not like a שטר קנין, shtar kinyan, right? It's
like saying, my last will and testament is that I want at
the moment of death that Gloria should get this field and Charlie
should get this and duh duh duh. It's not a שטר קנין,
shtar kinyan, it's a will. It's a written expression
of my bequest. Now, the relevance of that is that this will
is not effective, in law you need a will to be effective
you need it what, signed by witnesses? No, I guess if you
do it in your own handwriting it's probably good, right? Gloria, do
you know? I don't know. Okay, anyway, clearly you need some requirements
to be made for a will to be considered a legally binding
document. So for here, it's for it to be considered an effective
will, it has to be handed over. It's not a שטר קנין,
shtar kinyan, it only takes effect at the death etc. and might
doesn't even have the right language of a שטר קנין, shtar kinyan,
but nevertheless it only takes effect if it's handed over. So an
oral bequest is binding just by the oral utterance. Somewhere ironically, if
you don't utter it orally and you write it down, it is
not binding until it's handed over. Okay, so that's the basic principle.
The other thing you need to know is that a מתנת שכיב
מרע matnat shchiv meira can be reversed. A guy on his deathbed
the same way, I mean and again for us it's easier to
think about this in terms of a will. You can constantly be
revising your will, right? So the same way you can write a
will and revise it and revise it and revise it until the
moment you die, you can give a deathbed bequest and then retract
it the next day. Okay, but so again, a will is like
a written version of a deathbed bequest, the prime model for the
חז"ל chazal is not the will but the deathbed bequest. Okay, so
let's take a look at the משנה. mishnah. מי שמת, mi shemet,
somebody died, ונמצא דיאתיקי קשורה על יריכו, venimtsa diatiki kshura al yerecho,
and he had a will that was bound on his thigh, sort
of like אברהם שים נא ידך תחת ירכי, Avraham sim na yadecha
tachat yerecho, but the point is there is no question that this
is his will. He wrote it, it's bound on his thigh, it's
not somebody else dropped a will on his bed by accident or
on purpose. Okay, there's no question he wrote it. It doesn't matter.
הרי זה אינה כלום, harei zeh einah klum, it is completely non-effective,
the will has no is not binding until it is handed over.
זיכה בה לאחר, zichah bah l'acher, now
let's say he goes and he says, hey Joe, here pick up
this will for me, this is my will and I want it
to be effective, take hold of this will, okay, so זיכה בה
לאחר zichah bah l'acher בין מן היורשין בין שאינו מן היורשין bein
min hayorshin bein she'eino min hayorshin דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamim, whether it
is on behalf of heirs or not on behalf of heirs, okay,
it is binding. Now, the רשב"ם rashbam also says that the question
here on who is it behalf of, because why should it matter
who it's on behalf of? Obviously that the point of a will
is that the will doesn't even have a name in it. The
will doesn't even say, I hereby bequeath to Charlie, you know, my
real estate on Fifth Avenue or something. It just says, I hereby
bequeath. It just says I hereby bequeath to you or to my
real estate on Fifth Avenue and I give it to Charlie. So
even though it doesn't have any names in it, if that person
takes it, okay, it is effective and it's assumed to be to
be given to that in the absence of a name, it's assumed
to be a bequest to the person who's holding on to the
document. It's like a blank check, you know.
Okay. Alright, so that is the point of the משנה. Mishna. We
are finally getting into the wills. Okay.
Why is the why is the written document
ineffectual whereas in all other areas we've seen so far, a שטר
shtar serves as evidence or the
Well,
a normal שטר shtar that serves as evidence has witnesses signed on
it. This is not this is not witness as as a testimony
to a fact. This is just written as a bequest. I hereby
writing my last will and testament da da da da da da
da da.
Anyone could have written
this thing and tied it on to him. No, no, no. That's
not the question. That's why it says it's כתב ידו. ktav yado.
We have no question that he wrote it. But it's not effective.
If witnesses write a שטר, shtar, then they are testifying to something.
Here you're just a your just written expression of your desire of
your will to bequeath your property which is not a binding document
unless you get it somehow duly executed.
Because halakhically the because it's
just גילוי מילתא giluy milta basically, right?
Right, but but halakhically we have to create a halakhic instrument to
make it effective. The fact that if I know, if I can
prove in court that somebody wanted to give me their property, I
don't get their property if there's no properly executed will. The fact
of what somebody's desire is doesn't make it a legally binding act.
What makes somebody's bequest a legally binding act is either a verbal
deathbed bequest or a written will that's handed over. Those are the
legal instruments. Doesn't matter what somebody's desire is. I can bring mounds
and mounds of evidence that somebody wanted to am I wrong Gary
that somebody wanted to give me all their property am I wrong?
Okay, but in the absence of a will, then it just follows
the normal rules of inheritance.
But my question is why this isn't a will? Why isn't this
a will?
It is a will. It's not a properly executed will. A properly
executed will has to be handed over. Okay, you know, a will
is like duly signed and notarized or whatever? Okay, there's requirements for
a properly executed will. It has to be...
this is just a
shopping list on on the counter. It is not, it's a will
that he hasn't yet executed by because he hasn't yet done that
key act of handing it over. It's just a techno... like any
legal act,
it has requirements that have to be...
So he doesn't have to have witnesses to the handing over, just
have to hand it over?
Oh, that's a good question. If there are no witnesses to the
act, I mean, I guess then the question would become one of
of proving it, like you know, somebody would claim he never really
gave it to you. It's like the idea of the verbal deathbed
bequest. You don't need witnesses for it to be binding, but if
I come out of that room and I say oh, he just
gave me all his property if I prove it. So I guess
your point is that let's say it's in his handwriting, you know,
or let's say there's a we can there's enough right. So I
think that the answer is that witnesses aren't needed to make it
binding, but but you need to prove that it actually happened. So
if enough so if like it's in his own handwriting, right, and
I'm now holding the document, so that probably would be sufficient. I
have to check that but I do not believe witnesses are technically
needed.
Suppose he hands it to his next-door neighbor and in it names
that his kids are going to get stuff.
Right. Will that work? I yes, so the משנה Mishna is a
little unclear because the משנה Mishna says זיכה בה לאחר. zicha bah
leacher. Does that mean זיכה בה לאחר zicha bah leacher is he
gives it to the person he is who's the recipient of the
bequest, or does it mean לאחר leacher like I am מזכה mezakeh
to ראובן Reuven by giving it to
שמעון? Shimon? I mean, I imagine that the will could have twenty,
you know, beneficiaries and you're not giving it to all of them.
So I think the point is you just have to give it
to anybody else and you say take this will and by your
taking it it makes it like binding. I believe. But I I
will get back to you on that exactly.
Is that sort of like a קנין סודר?
kinyan sudar? Right, exactly. But again, the difference is is that without
the rabbinic institution of a will this wouldn't work
because because first of all, the language might not be written as
a שטר קנין shtar kinyan and it's only effective at the person's
death and a real קנין kinyan has to work while the person
is still alive. So yes, there could be similar ways you could
do it that could work through normal rules of קנינים, kinyanim, but
this is but because of the way this is phrased and because
of when it takes effect, it's really only working as a will
and not as a normal קנין. kinyan.
Yes. But see what we're asking is we've been calling it for
a form of the formalism of it's got to be a legally
executed document. Right. Well, but there's always a reason for that.
It's not just a Yeah, because of a question about גמירות דעת
gmirat daat and when is he really finalized in his right.
In other words, this document as it's tied to his thigh so
to speak without being executed is got
is is it's missing the גמירות דעת.
gmirat daat. Because it has not yet been communicated to somebody else.
Now the irony is that a verbal statement is more binding than
a written document that hasn't been handed over. But the point is
that a verbal statement still is heard by somebody else. Right, exactly.
The verbal statement has to be heard.
Right. To himself no one's hearing it. If he was mumbling to
himself and I was listening at the door that would not count.
A verbal statement is communicated to somebody else.
What if he's in a room full
of people who
are deaf?